Register of the Perrin C. Galpin Papers, 1914-1957
Hoover Institution Archives
Perrin C. Galpin Papers,
1914-1957.
57015
Galpin, Perrin C., 1889-1973.
6 manuscript boxes, 2 envelopes (2.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, photographs, clippings, and printed matter, relating to the Commission for Relief in Belgium, the American Relief Administration, Herbert Hoover and American electoral politics, and the 1938 trip to Europe and 1946 food relief activities in Europe of Herbert Hoover.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1957.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Commission for Relief in Belgium (1914-1930); American Relief Administration.; United States. President's Famine Emergency Committee.; International relief.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; Belgium.; United States--Politics and government.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.
Biographical Note
1889, August 11 Born, New Haven, Connecticut
1913-1914 Graduate studies, Oxford University, Great Britain
1914-1915 Secretary, Commission for Relief in Belgium (Brussels)
1916-1917 Instructor of history and economics, Union College, Schenectady, New York
1917-1918 Served as a captain of field artillery in the U.S. Army in France
1918-1919 Secretary, Commission for Relief in Belgium (Lille)
1919-1923 Secretary, American Relief Administration
1920 Original incorporator, Belgian-Ameircan Educational Foundation; President until 1963
1923 Incorporator, American Children's Fund; Vice-President from 1936 to 1950
1928 Honorary Doctorate, University of Louvain, Belgium
1930 Honorary Doctorate, University of Brussels, Belgium
1932- Member, Francqui Foundation of Belgium
1938 Accompanied Herbert Hoover on his trip to Europe
1945- Member, Council of Administration, Fondation Universitaire de Belgique
1945-1955 Director, W. T. Grant Co.
1946 Member, Herbert Hoover Food Mission to Europe and Asia
1947-1955 Executive Director, Grant Foundation
1951 Decorated Grand Officer of Leopold II, Belgium
1956 Editor: Hugh Gibson, 1883-1954
1973, August 11 Died, Pelham Manor, New York
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, reports, photographs, clippings, and printed matter, relating to the Commission for Relief in Belgium, the American Relief Administration, Herbert Hoover and American electoral politics, and the 1938 trip to Europe and 1946 food relief activities in Europe of Herbert Hoover.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1914-1946 (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Appointment as special investigator during presidential elections, 1928 (Box 1.)
  - Insurance policy contracted for trip to Europe, 1938 (Box 1.)
  - Newspaper clippings on Galpin and his trip to Europe and Asia, 1946 (Box 1.)
  - Safe-conducts issued by the German authorities in Belgium, 1914-1915 (Box 1.)
- Correspondence, 1914-1955.See also Subject File, Hoover, Herbert, Presidential campaigns, 1928, Corresondence of Galpin (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Unidentified, 1945-1946 (Box 1.)
  - American Relief Administration. See Subject File, A.R.A.
  - Anonymous (on the world food situation), 1946 (Box 1.)
  - Bane, Suda L., 1939-1945 (Box 1.)
  - Bottorff, Ann, 1955 (Box 1.)
  - Commission for Relief in Belgium, Brussels, 1915 (Box 1.)
  - Dupuis, Emile, 1915 (Box 1.)
  - Fisher, Harold H.
    - 1934-1939 (Box 1.)
    - 1940-1949 (Box 1.)
    - 1950-1955 (Box 1.)
  - Galpin, Anne Perrin (Penny) (daughter), 1938 (Box 1.)
  - Galpin, Harry (brother), 1914-1915 (including a letter to his wife, Ellen) (Box 1.)
  - Galpin, Lucy K. E. (daughter), 1946 (Box 1.)
  - Galpin, Stephanie (wife), 1938-1946 (Box 1.)
  - Galpin, Mrs. Henry L., 1938 (Box 1.)
  - Hoover, Herbert (mostly on Rhodes Scholars), 1914-1928 (Box 1.)
  - Jessup, Philip C., 1943 (Box 1.)
  - Lucey, Captain J. F., 1914 (Box 1.)
  - Mitchell, P. V. G. (U.S. Lines), 1938 (Box 1.)
  - Murray, Major C. P., Jr., 1945 (Box 1.)
  - Roscoe, 1938 (Box 1.)
  - Special Aid Society for American Preparedness, 1938 (Box 1.)
  - Telegrams wishing Galpin a good trip and welcoming him back, 1938 (Box 1.)
- Speeches and Writings, 1932-1946 (Box 2)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "As President," 1932. Typewritten carbon copy of the draft for a 3 page essay on Herbert Hoover (Box 2.)
  - Letters to the editor. See Subject File, Hoover, Herbert, Presidential campaigns, 1920 and 1928, letters to the editor by Galpin
  - Notes on the Commission for Relief in Belgium, n.d. Handwriten copy (Box 2.)
  - Notes on trip of 1946. Handwritten copy (Box 2.)
  - Remarks on the Westchester county (N.Y.) elections of March 19, 1935. Typewritten carbon copy (Box 2.)
  - Review of Leon Trotsky: Stalin. An Appraisal of the Man and His Influence, n.d. (including a letter accompanying the review sent to H. H. Fisher, June 7, 1944). Typewritten carbon copy (Box 2.)
  - Speech, Hopkins Grammar School, New Haven, Conn., June 18, 1938 (on trip of 1938). Typewritten carbon copy (Box 2.)
  - Speech, Pelham Men's Club, Pelham, N.Y., April 12, 1938 (on trip of 1938). Typewritten copy (Box 2.)
  - Speech (notes for), Staten Island, October 26, 1932 (on Hoover's presidential campaign). Typewritten copy (Box 2.)
  - Speech, Women's Republican Club, Poughkeepsie, September 1932 (On Hoover's presidential campaign). Two typewritten copies, one original and one carbon copy (Box 2.)
  - "Through Europe with Mr. Hoover, February and March 1938. Random notes, personal and confidential," dictated early in April in New York. Two typewritten copies, one original and one carbon copy (Box 2.)
- Subject File, 1914-1957 (Boxes 2-6)
  Clippings, correspondence, memorabilia, notes, printed matter, studies, arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - American Expeditionary Forces Headquarters, district of Paris, 1918 (Box 2.)
  - American Relief Administration (mostly Galpin's correspondence)
    - March-May 1921 (Box 2.)
    - June 1921-September 1927 (Box 6.)
  - Anglo-French Pact (new efforts to negotiate,), 1946 (Box 6.)
  - Asia, 1946 (Box 6.)
  - Austria, 1938 (Box 6.)
  - Belgium, 1914-1918. See Germany, occupation of Belgium (Box 2.)
  - Boulanger, Nadia, 1938 (Box 6.)
  - Commission for Relief in Belgium, 1914-1917
    - Articles on the work of (Box 6.)
    - Articles on the accomplishments of Delegates (Box 6.)
    - Galpin's work appraised by others (Box 6.)
    - Memorabilia (Box 2.)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6.)
    - Publications (Box 2.)
    - Rationing (Box 6.)
    - Reports (Box 2.)
    - Rhodes Scholars. See also CORRESPONDENCE, Hoover, Herbert (Box 6.)
    - Safe-conduct for two C.R.B. vehicles (Box 6.)
  - "The Development of Finnish-Soviet Relations during the autumn of 1939" published by the Ministry for Foreign Affairs of Finland, 1940 (Box 2.)
  - Donovan, Colonel Bill (ran for Governor of New York in 1932) (Box 3.)
  - Fisher, Harold H., 1952-1957. For curriculum vitae, See CORRESPONDENCE, Fisher, H. H., February 27, 1945 (Box 3.)
  - Galpin, Ellen D. (letter of thanks from C.R.B. Vice-Chairman Lindon W. Bates and certificate of acknowledgment for her donation to the C.R.B., 1915) (Box 3.)
  - Galpin, Stephanie (letter from an unidentified friend, April 9, 1946) (Box 3.)
  - Galpin, Stephen K. (letters to the family, 1946, see also CORRESPONDENCE, Fisher, H. H., March 8, 1945, and to Harold H. Fisher, 1950). See also Subject File, Hoover, Herbert, Correspondence, Galpin, Stephen K. (Box 3.)
  - Germany
    - Occupation of Belgium, 1914-1918
      - Articles on (Box 3.)
      - Atrocities perpetrated (Box 3.)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3.)
      - Proclamations (Box 3.)
    - Survey of the Reichstag election of March 5, 1933 (Box 3.)
    - Treaty of Peace with, 1919 (Box 3.)
  - Gibson, Hugh S. (letters to Harry L. Galpin. 1915, and to Mrs. Hoover, 1938) (Box 3.)
  - Great Britain (supplies for Belgian industries), 1916 (Box 3.)
  - Grey, Sir Edward. See Commission for Relief in Belgium, Publications (Box 3.)
  - Hall, Representative Edwin Arthur, 1946 (Box 3.)
  - Holland (schemes for raising revenue) (Box 3.)
  - Hoover, Herbert
    - Articles on, 1935-1939 (Box 3.)
    - Correspondence
      - Unidentified, 1915 (Hoover on C.R.B.) (Box 3.)
      - Galpin, Stephen K., 1933 (Box 3.)
    - Presidential campaigns
      - 1920, Race for the Republican nomination
        - General (Box 3.)
        - Galpin's letters to the editor (Box 3.)
      - 1928
        - Articles (Box 3.)
        - Biographical data on Herbert Hoover (Box 3.)
        - Campaign books of both parties (Box 3.)
        - Galpin's correspondence (with Angell, A.R.A. men, Baker, Cross, Flesh, Fox, Gibney, Gutterson, Hoffman, Hubbard, Hutchinson Kott?, Nash?, New York Engineers Hoover Committee, Richards, Richey, Rickards, Surface, Tilson) (Box 3.)
        - Electoral estimates and results (Box 3.)
        - Financial matters (Box 3.)
        - Hoover-Curtis University Committee for Connecticut (Box 3.)
        - Instructions for election day based on election law (Box 3.)
        - Letters to the editor
          - Galpin's (Box 3.)
          - Others' (Box 3.)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 3.)
        - New York Engineers' Hoover Committee (Box 3.)
        - New York Young Republican Club (Box 3.)
        - Newspaper clippings
          - General (Box 3.)
          - On the candidates (Box 3.)
          - On the issues (prohibition, immigration, religion, Hoover's relief work, water power, etc.) (Box 3.)
        - Politricks (Box 3.)
        - Publications of both parties (Box 4.)
        - Publicity for Hoover (Box 4.)
        - Speeches and statements
          - By Herbert Hoover (Box 4.)
          - By Al Smith (Box 4.)
          - By others (Box 4.)
      - 1932
        - Articles and letters in favor of Hoover (Box 4.)
        - Galpin's correspondence (with Hinshaw, Morgan, Strauss) (Box 4.)
        - Material gathered on Franklin D. Roosevelt and Haiti (including Galpin's research notes on the question) (Box 4.)
        - New York Young Republican Club (Box 4.)
        - Publicity and publication of both parties, including reprints of speeches by both candidates (Box 4.)
    - Speeches, 1926-1953 (Box 4.)
    - Trips
      - 1938, to Europe
        - Binder containing newspaper clippings, telegrams, photographs, invitations, menus, speeches, postcards, bills, etc. (Box 4.)
        - Countries visited
          - Austria (Box 4.)
          - Belgium (Box 4.)
          - Czechoslovakia (Box 4.)
          - France (Box 4.)
          - Germany (Box 4.)
          - Great Britain (Box 5.)
          - Poland (Box 5.)
        - Itineraries (Box 5.)
        - Newspaper clippings
          - General (Box 5.)
          - Before departure (Box 5.)
        - Return to the United States. Address by Herbert Hoover at the Council on Foreign Affairs, March 21, 1938 (Box 5.)
        - S.S. Normandie (Box 5.)
      - 1946, to Europe and Asia, as honorary chairman of President Truman's Famine Emergency Commitee
        - Conversion rates of foreign currencies (Box 5.)
        - Countries visited
          - Czechoslovakia (Box 5.)
          - Germany (Box 5.)
          - Great Britain (Box 5.)
          - Egypt (Box 5.)
          - India (Box 5.)
          - Japan (Box 5.)
          - Norway (Box 5.)
          - Poland (Box 5.)
          - Siam (Thailand) (Box 5.)
        - Food situation (articles, reports, etc.) (Box 5.)
        - Itinerary (Box 5.)
        - Mason, Frank E. Reports of trips (Box 5.)
        - Newspaper clippings (including those from the Daily News and others in a binder) (Box 5.)
        - "Random vital statistics" (Box 5.)
  - Hoover Overseas and War Service Organizations 1914-1924, 1929 (Box 5.)
  - Iran, 1946 (Box 5.)
  - Navigation science. A review of Lawrence C. Wrath's The Way of a Ship: An Essay on the Literature of Navigation, Science, 1939, by Lincoln Colcord O'Hare, Anne McCormick (N.Y. Times correspondent in Europe), 1938-1946 (Box 5.)
  - Official Directory for 1776 State National Committeemen (Box 5.)
  - Poland Fights, April-May 1946 (Box 5.)
  - La Province, February 26, 1930 (Box 5.)
  - Rickard, Edgar (on Hoover), 1928 (Box 5.)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano. See also Hoover, Herbert, Presidential campaigns, 1932, material gathered on F.D.R. and Haiti; Smith, Al
    - General (Box 5.)
    - Inaugural Address, March 4, 1933 (Box 5.)
  - Rugby Union, 1946 (Box 5.)
  - Smith, Al, relations with Franklin Delano Roosevelt (Box 5.)
  - Smith, Paul C. (accompanied Hoover on his trip to Europe in 1938), articles in the San Francisco Chronicle, April 1938 (Box 5.)
  - Time Magazine, "Background for War" (special issue), 1938 (Box 5.)
  - United Nations Organization, Military Staff Committee meeting in New York, March 1946, to submit plans for an international police force to the Security Council) (Box 5.)
  - Zeeland, Paul van. Report on International Economic Reconstruction, March 1938 (Box 5.)
- Increment
  - Album with metal covers, embossed title "Remerciements" and flowers. Watercolor illustration and letters of thanks, and a poem. "Le Comité des Dames de Montegne, Liége à la noble Amérique!", 1915; Received from Perrin Galpin 1966 (Box 5.)
  - Materials re. CRB, including identification papers for Perrin Galpin (one with photograph), and two postcards to Henry Galpin (Box 5.)
- Memorabilia, 1928
  - Memorabilia, 1928. One oversize folder containing two copies of Galpin's honorary doctorate from the University of Louvain, Belgium, May 25, 1928 (Shelf On Shelf)
- Photographs, 1938-1946., (27 photographs / 2 envelopes
  - 10 photographs depicting Herbert Hoover on his trip to Europe on board of SS Normandie and in Belgium, accompanied by Perrin C. Galpin and Paul C. Smith, 1938 (Folder A)
  - 17 photographs depicting Herbert Hoover on his trip to Europe and Asia, at the Vatican, in Poland, Greece and Norway, 1946 (Folder B)